Charles F. Lummis papers, 1559-1973
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Charles F. Lummis collection, 1559-1973
MS 039
Lummis, Charles Fletcher, 1859-1928
The collection includes correspondence (1879-1928), biographical materials and memorabilia (1884-1973), photographs (1889-1928), and historical materials (1559-1932), including original and typescript historical documents mainly from Spain and California.
2.1 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Charles Fletcher Lummis was born in Lynn, Massachusetts on March 1, 1859, and died in Los Angeles on November 25, 1928. He was educated at home, and later attended Harvard University until 1881. He soon moved to Chillicothe, Ohio, where he briefly managed his father-in-law's farm before taking a job as reporter, and later as editor, with the local newspaper Scioto Gazette.
He introduced himself to the West on foot during his famous 143 day walk from Cincinnati to Los Angeles. He began work there as editor of Harrison G. Otis' newspaper, The Los Angeles Times.
From 1885 on, Los Angeles was his base from which he explored, defended, and promoted the Southwest. His energy and enthusiasm were as broad as the land he loved. He investigated the Apache Wars in Arizona in 1886, recovered from a stroke and shooting in New Mexico, traveled with Adolph Bandelier to Peru, edited one of the most progressive periodicals of the region Land of Sunshine and Out West, built a monumental hilltop home El Alisal, and served as librarian to the Los Angeles Public Library. His aggressive drive to establish permanent cultural institutions and civic traditions culminated in his work for the Landmark Club, Sequoya League, and, closest to his heart, the Southwest Society and its Southwest Museum
A prolific promoter of the Southwest and California history, Lummis wrote many books on the area including A New Mexico David, Some Strange Corners of Our Country, A Tramp Across the Continent, and The Land of Poco Tiempo. His poetry, articles and reviews were also widely distributed in the leading magazines of his day. His friends ranged from Presidents to fisherman. His favored causes, such as pristine lands, native peoples, or historical monuments, were empowered by his forceful advocacy in print and in person of their collective needs.
Lummis was married and divorced from Dorothea Rhodes (1880-1891), Eva Frances Douglas (1891-1910), and Gertrude Redit (1915-192?). His children were Bertha Belle Page, b. 1879, Dorothea Turbese, 1892-1968, Amado Bandelier, 1894-1900, Jordan (Quimu), b. 1900, and Keith, 1904-1991.
Organization
This collection is organized into five series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1879-1928
Series II: Biographical Materials and Memorabilia, 1884-1973
Series III: Photographs, 1889-1928
Series IV: Works, 1887-1927
Series V: Historical Materials, 1559-1932
Scope and Content Note
The Correspondence, 1879-1928, includes members of the Lummis family, admirers of his writing, literary colleagues like Hamlin Garland, and political friends that include President Theodore Roosevelt and Major General Leonard Wood.
The Biographical materials and memorabilia, 1884-1973, includes miscellaneous personal items, autobiographical notes including the incomplete typescript of his memoirs, "As I Remember," with different versions and rewrites by his daughter, Turbese. Also includes extracts from Lummis' journal, clippings and a scrapbook.
The Photographs, 1889-1928, including over 300 photographs, many of which are cyanotypes. They depict Lummis throughout his life; his family; his home "El Alisal" being built in 1904; various places he visited; and friends, such as the historian Sharlot Hall, the naturalist John Burroughs, and the artist William Keith. Photographs of the Pueblo Indians date from 1889 to 1896; Acoma and Isleta Pueblos are the most represented. A smaller group of photographs from 1902 depicts Mohave Indians in Needles, California.
Historical materials, 1559-1932, including original and typescript historical documents mainly from Spain and California. The original Spanish ones are a 1559 manuscript concerning the reform of the royal hospital near Burgos, Spain; a 1584 manuscript relating the legal history of this hospital from the 1450's to the 1580's; and a 1613 "purity of blood" testimonial attesting to the non-Jewish background of Estaban Ruiz of Santa Marta, Spain. Among the original California documents are a 1796 manuscript, in Spanish, relating to the Santa Cruz Mission; an 1849 list of ship passengers on board the "Orpheus," from New York to San Francisco; and an 1883 narration, in Spanish, on the century's events in California: including the arrival of the Americans, Santa Ana, and the first printing enterprise.
Access Terms
Lummis, Charles Fletcher, 1859-1928 -- Archives
Southwest Museum (Los Angeles, Calif.) -- History
Mohave Indians -- Photographs
Pueblo Indians -- Photographs
Indians of North America -- Southwest, New -- Photographs
Antisemitism -- Spain -- History -- 17th century -- Sources
Hospitals -- Spain -- History -- 16th century -- Sources
Ships -- Passenger lists
Santa Cruz Mission -- History -- 18th century -- Sources
California -- History -- 19th century -- Sources
Correspondence
Photographs
Scrapbooks
Related Material
MS 37 Frances Douglas Papers, and MS 297 Charles F. Lummis Papers.
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1879-1928
  - Correspondence. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence. 1879-1888 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence. 1889-1917 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence. 1918-1928 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: Biographical materials and memorabilia, 1884-1973
  - Southwest Museum, Los Angles. Photographs, floor plans; article by C.F.L. published in North American Review; Article by Phil T. Hanna, "Nestor on the Amerinds," about F.W. Hodge, published in Touring Topics. August 1928 and February 1932 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Indians. Notes and articles (holograph, typescript). No Date (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous personal items. No Date (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Autobiographical notes. No Date (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "As I Remember" part 1. No Date (Box 2, Folder 3a)
  - "As I Remember" part 2. No Date (Box 2, Folder 3b)
  - "As I Remember" edited by T.L. No Date (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "As I Remember" re-writes and fragments. No Date (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Extracts from C.F.L.'s journal. No Date (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series III: Photographs, 1889-1928
  - Lummis. No Date, 93 photos, some duplicates (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "El Alisal." No Date, 77 photos (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Family, mother, father, sister. No Date, 6 photos (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Trip to New York, Washington, etc. 1901, 15 photos (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Cave dwellings. No Date, 4 photos (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Penitentes. No Date, 5 photos (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Pueblo Indians. No Date, 58 photos (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - California. No Date, 17 photos (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Arizona. No Date, 19 photos (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Friends. No Date, 10 photos (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous New Mexico. No Date, 13 photos (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous, mostly unidentified. No Date, 23 photos (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Series IV: Works, 1887-1927
  - Articles (holograph, typescript, printed). No Date (Box 3b, Folder 1-2)
  - Poems. No Date (Box 3b, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous biographical material by others. No Date (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Clippings. 1888-1953 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Series V: Historical Material, 1559-1932
  - Various Spanish Documents. No Date (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Various American Documents. No Date (Box 4, Folder 4)